Okay, so today's דף daf is נ"ד. Nun Dalet. We're a little
bit behind, we're in the middle of the אגדתא Agadata on נ"ג
עמוד ב', Nun Gimmel Amud Beis, and let's take a look. Okay,
אמר
רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, about a third of the way down.
The line starts with the word זו Zo and then there's a
little bit of a רש"י Rashi base and half bracket. Okay, see
where it is? אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, about 15 lines
down. בשעה שחרב בית המקדש, Be-Sha'ah Shecharav Beis Hamikdash, so this אגדתא
Agadata was brought in in the past that we did, which was
just because it was the same רבי כרידא. Rabbi Creeda. Now at
least we're bringing it in somewhat into the קדשים Kodshim context to
talk about the חורבן הבית Churban HaBayis and this אגדתא Agadata will
connect with a פסוק Pasuk that we had quoted yesterday. בשעה שחרב
בית המקדש, Be-Sha'ah Shecharav Beis Hamikdash, when the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
was destroyed, מצא הקדוש ברוך הוא ואברהם, Matza HaKadosh Baruch Hu v'Avraham,
God found Abraham who was שהיה עומד בבית המקדש, Shehayah Omed Beis
Hamikdash, and he was standing in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אמר
לו, Amar lo, He said to him, מה לידידי בביתי, Ma liy'didi
b'veisi, what is my beloved one doing in my house? Right, we
had that פסוק Pasuk yesterday that we know that Abraham would call
beloved, so what is my beloved one doing in my house? אמר
לו, Amar lo, so Abraham said, על עסקי בני באתי, Al iskei
banai bati, I came because of my children, they've been, their temple's
been destroyed and they've been sent into exile. אמר לו, Amar lo,
so God said to him, hey don't complain to me, בניך חטאו
וגלו, Banecha chatu v'galu, they sinned and they were punished, they were
sent into exile. אמר לו, Amar lo, so Abraham said to
God, שמא בשוגג חטאו, Shema bishogeg chatu, you know, maybe they did
it unintentionally, they didn't deserve their punishment. אמר לו, Amar lo, so
השם Hashem said back to him, עשותה המזימתה, Asosah hamizimatah, they have
done, you know, מזימה Mezimah is like to plan and willfully. And
now we're quoting a whole series of פסוקים Psukim from ירמיהו Yirmiyahu
where actually in the פסוקים Psukim themselves God is, you know, it's
like what is ירמיהו Yirmiyahu doing in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
it's the פסוקים Psukim are prophesying the destruction of the temple, but
here it is placing the dialogue the other side to be with
Abraham, not with ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. אמר לו, Amar lo, so Abraham said
to Him, שמא מיעוטם חטאו, Shema mi'utam chatu, maybe it was only
a minority, maybe it wasn't a majority, they didn't deserve this punishment.
אמר לו, Amar lo, God said to him, הרבים, Harabim, they were,
it was the, the masses. So Abraham said back to God, היה
לך לזכור ברית מילה, Haya lecha lizkor Bris Milah, you should have
remembered the ברית מילה Bris Milah that they kept presumably, not interesting
when you say ברית מילה Bris Milah and Abraham, you're thinking it's
talking about Abraham having kept it, but the context here is if
they kept it, at least that should have come to their credit.
אמר לו, Amar lo, so God said back to him, ובשר קודש
יעברו מעליך, Uv'sar kodesh ya'avru me'alecha, the holy flesh they will pass
away from, from you, which means that it's being read as that
they, you know, they covered up their ברית מילה Bris Milah or
they did surgery. What? Oh, or they didn't do it, that could
be too, but depends how, you know, if we're reading it in
terms of the בית שני, Bayis Sheni, the גמרא Gemara was definitely
well aware of the, of there was a practice in Hellenistic times
to reverse the ברית מילה. Bris Milah. So I thought that's how
I was reading it, but you know, יעברו מעליך, Ya'avru me'alecha, you
could write מיעוט Mi'ut to be over and something means to pass
by and not do
it.
Either way, it all sounds like when Abraham was asking how many,
it's like the question about Sodom and Gomorrah, that same kind
of...
yeah, you know, it's obviously that was invoking that from me as
well and I think what's particularly fascinating here is that Abraham is
coming after the fact. Like a little bit late to be complaining
after the fact, they're already, the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is already
destroyed, they're already in גלות, Galus, and essentially what is he asking
for, he's just saying God this wasn't just and not even unclear
what he's trying to get out of it, he's just saying this
wasn't just, which is very much the whole thing with, you know,
Abraham and Sodom and Gomorrah who was trying to protect them, but
it was about sort of like standing for justice. Did they really
deserve this? And it is a little strange, you know, what, how
to understand, like, how's the גמרא Gemara understanding this, what is he
trying to get out of playing to pray to God after the
fact? We'll feel to see how it is. The other interesting question
to ask is why is it being cast as Abraham? I mean,
yes, we said before, Abraham was ידידי, Yedidi, but they had some,
they had some intuitive understanding that they saw this as Abraham in
the פשט Pshat of the פסוקים Psukim in ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, it wasn't
Abraham, it was ירמיהו Yirmiyahu that was having this conversation with God,
so that's another interesting question to ask.
So if he went to where the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was,
don't say that he's not good, he's just there.
Right, and God says hey what are you doing here?
So he wasn't at the site of הר המוריה Har HaMoriah with
עקידה? Akeidah?
Oh, that's an interesting point. Yeah, yeah, that's an interesting point. Although
appropriate to be the person there by the, a lot of people
have experiences there, יעקב, Yaakov, you know, a lot of people were
having experiences at הר הבית. Har HaBayis. So, but alright, Abraham maybe
first. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר לו, Amar lo, so
Abraham said to God, שמא המתנת להם היו חוזרים בתשובה, Shema himtanta
lahem hayu chozrim bitshuvah, you know God you could have waited, maybe
they would have done תשובה, Tshuvah, well you didn't have to punish
them so quickly. So אמר לו, Amar lo, God said back to
Abraham, כי רעתכי אז תעלוזי, Ki ra'asaychi az ta'alozi,
their evil then they will rejoice, which רש"י Rashi says means basically
they rejoice, you know, the more evil they do the more they
rejoice, there was no hope they were definitely not going to do
תשובה. Tshuvah. But you know, Bobby is certainly correct that the point
here is, you know, Abraham makes a claim, God has an answer,
Abraham makes a claim, God has an answer, like Abraham keeps is
not letting go and he's working as hard as he can. מיד
הניח ידו על ראשו והיה צועק ובוכה. Miyad haniach yado al rosho
vehayah tzo'ek uvoche.
So Abraham placed his hands on his head and he you know
obviously was like you know sat down and started crying ואמר לו
v'amar lo and he said to God שמא חס ושלום אין להם
תקנה shema chas v'shalom ein lahem takana maybe they have no way
of becoming fixed meaning maybe that's it they're gone they'll never come
back to the land of Israel because of course Abraham was promised
you know that the children would come into the land after the
whole period of exile of being in מצרים Mitzrayim so obviously you
understand that he here is very concerned that obviously they will survive
and come back.
But by the way if you stop for a moment and reflect
and ask yourself in all of the imagery of the people crying
you know the previous generations crying over the destruction of the Temple
praying to God that the children come back I don't think any
of us think of Abraham. You know the stories first of all
the פסוקים pesukim have you know רחל מבכה על בניה Rachel mevaka
al baneha
you know and so on but it's quite interesting that Abraham is
not normally cast in this role. Here he is okay so ואמר
לו v'amar lo so God said back to him יצתה בת קול
ואמרה
לו yatzta bat kol v'amra lo a heavenly voice came out and
said to him interesting now it's not God now it's a heavenly
voice maybe God is being cast as the מידת הדין Middat Ha-Din
and you need this heavenly voice. Also if you want to talk
about evoking images by Abraham God says right God does take your
son at the sacrifice and then it's the angel that comes and
saves the day so here the heavenly voice came out and said
right with the tears Isaac oh
yeah according to the מדרש midrash right right. But anyway so here's
the heavenly voice that comes and saves the day ואמר לו v'amar
lo and says to him זית רענן יפה פרי תואר קרא ה׳
שמך Zayit ra'anan yafeh pri to'ar kara Hashem shmecha
a flourishing olive tree of beautiful fruit God has called your name.
So מה זית זה אחריתו בסופו ma zayit zeh achrito b'sofo the
same way an olive tree the you know the benefit it comes
at the end you know so they say that means that you
know it takes a while after it's planted till finally all of
the olives come out or the way תוספות Tosafot says it means
that the olives are harvested not little by little but then you
know they're all unripe and then at one stage they all become
ripe so there's you know you have to sort of wait to
the end to reap the benefits so אף
ישראל אחריתן בסופן af Yisrael achritan b'sofan and the same
is true with the Jewish people in the end it'll all be
good now it's a very difficult time. Okay so we're about to
shift but let me just say one thing about this. So again
it is quite fascinating that Abraham is being cast here as the
one praying it's not normally Abraham yet it does evoke other things
about Abraham.
A point that I made in a post I did yesterday tying
in you know the discussion the other day about
which were Rav Preada and Ibn Ezra about like is it about
you know your ancestors or is it about what you've accomplished is
that what's also quite fascinating here is that Abraham never says you
know היה לך לזכור לאברהם יצחק ויעקב haya lach lizkor l'Avraham Yitzchak
v'Ya'akov right like how about remember what Abraham, Isaac and Jacob did
that's what we always say. Well but okay but he's trying to
say not the he's trying to say you know to do good
for כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael and even when he says ברית מילה
brit mila it's also like if Abraham's talking about ברית מילה brit
mila you expect it to be talking about you know what Abraham
did not what the children did and what's quite fascinating that all
of that is basically completely ignored and passed over and it seems
to be much fitting into you know sort of Rav Preada's approach
which it's not what your forefathers did it's what you've accomplished so
even when Abraham is praying he's praying for what you know to
judge them judge them favorably but for their doings not his so
I do think that's interesting that here the גמרא Gemara is bracketing
the whole זכות אבות zechut avot and actually if I mentioned this
in the post I put up yesterday remember what Rav Preada said
Rav Preada said if you're not a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and
your parents were תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim if you're not living up
you know to their example
then a fire should consume you
upon which there a fire consumes the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash so
in some way this might be very much you know
echoing Rav Preada's approach how it's casting it but it's still quite
fascinating casting Abraham in that role of praying for them and it's
more about and it does evoke the whole Sodom and Amora not
usually how we see Abraham.
It also is maybe what you said earlier that Abraham said look
ה׳ Hashem you know we had an understanding
together right
right well that's why the גמרא Gemara right and that's what's so
funny because that understanding otherwise known as a ברית brit right and
and I remember וזכרתי את בריתי יעקב ואף את בריתי יצחק ואף
את בריתי אברהם אזכור v'izkarti et briti Ya'akov v'af et briti Yitzchak
v'af et briti Avraham ezkor right that's always in the תורה Torah
right and here it's completely being ignored it's not about the ברית
brit of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob it's about them being judged on
their own terms even with Abraham praying for them so I do
think it's like an extreme application almost maybe about Rav Preada
you know that point.
So let's take a look. I don't have an answer for but
that's just you know basically emphasizing if you really want to judge
people always just on their own so sometimes you know here's what
you get out of it. So okay now the גמרא Gemara continues
לקול המולה גדולה l'kol hamula gedola to the sound of the great
tumult so הצית אש עליה hetzit esh aleha fire has been lit
upon it here's the הצית אש hetzit esh about the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash actually was that the same Was that
the phrase אש תוכלהו? eish tochlaso? Yeah. אש תכלה, Eish tichleh, תכלה
tichleh
it means
to destroy, להכלה, lehachaloh, I mean it means תאכל. tochal. But anyway
it wasn't exactly the same phrase. Anyway, back to this. הצית אש
עליה, Hietit eish aleha, fire has been lit. ורעעו דליותיו Vera'au daliyosav
and its, it's you know, its what do they call those? The
young plantlings? Plantlings? The young shoots are going to be shattered, you
know, shook, shaken up. This is about the this is about obviously
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא: Amar Rabbi
Chanina bar Pappa: לכל מילה שמרגלים, Lechol mila shemeraglim, המולה hamulah is
being used as the word, to the sound of the words of
the of the spies, נתרעעו דליותיהן של ישראל, nitra'au daliyoseihen shel Yisrael,
the very foundations of Israel, the small little shoots, plants were shaken
at their
base and our future was was endangered, you know, whether we would
survive. דאמר רבי חנינא בר פפא: D'amar Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa: דבר
גדול דיברו מרגלים באותה שעה. Davar gadol dibru meraglim b'osah sha'ah. A
very large thing, doesn't mean a good thing or an important thing,
but a very bad big thing, like you know, a terrible
thing, the
spies spoke at that time. כי חזק הוא ממנו, Ki chazak hu
mimennu, what they said, they are greater than we, talking about the
people in the land of כנען. Kena'an. אל תקרי ממנו, Al tikri
mimennu, don't read from we, אלא ממנו, ela mimennu, from him. Now,
some say that there is a difference if you some of the
texts even hear some say ממנו mimennu but ממנו. mimenno. But actually
as רש"י Rashi points out that there is no different pronunciation between
if ממנו mimennu means from us or from him. Okay, so it
doesn't really mean that you read the word differently, so what does
the word mean? It's not just saying that the, you know, the
people in the land of כנען Kena'an are greater than we are.
They are even greater than God, they'll resist God's ability, desire, you
know, ability to let us go in and conquer the land. כביכול
שאפילו בעל הבית אינו יכול להוציא כליו משם. Kiviyachol she'afillu ba'al habayis
eino yachol l'hotzi eilav misham. The owner, you know, like bandits have
taken over your house, and the owner can't even get back into
his house to take out his vessels. So they've taken over the
land of כנען Kena'an and God is unable to conquer them. So
implicitly, you know, it's a nice דרש, drash, but they're basically that's
what he's saying, that that's implicitly what they were saying. If they're
saying we can't conquer, they're saying God can't conquer. And that's how
what the מרגלים meraglim did was so terrible, so blasphemous that it
really should have, you know, could have brought total destruction to the
people of
ישראל. Yisrael. מתקיף לה רבי חייא בר חנינא, Matkif lah Rabbi Chiya
bar Chanina, or רבי חייא בר
אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba points out: האי לכל המולה גדולה, Hai
lechol hamulah gedolah, it shouldn't say המולה hamulah which means like maybe
a you know a tumult. According to you it should have said
לכל מילה lechol milah or מולה mola מבעי ליה, mibay'ei lei, which
would have meant word. Okay, so that's not a good פשט pshat
in the פסוקים. psukim. אלא אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Ela amar Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, here's the פשט pshat in the פסוקים. psukim. לאברהם, L'Avraham,
God said back to אברהם, Avraham, going back to our narrative before,
קולך שמעתי, kolcha shamati, I've heard your voice, וחמלתי עליהם, vachamalti aleihem,
and I have had compassion on them. This is a play with
reversing a ה heh and a ח. ches. We did it before,
if you remember on the עמוד א amud aleph where it said
מנחה תהיה, minchah tihiyeh, we said תהיה, tihiyeh, תחיה. tichyeh.
So we sometimes play with the ה heh and the ח. ches.
I think, as I'm not incorrect, that in that in some of
the script from this period it was even was pretty indecipherable. I
mean, for us it's indecipherable, it's a little gap, but even less
indecipherable, they were less careful when they wrote a ה heh to
make it look different from the ח. ches. Okay, so that allowed
them to play with the idea of reversing a ה heh and
a ח. ches. So therefore they said, it's not המולה גדולה hamulah
gedolah but חמולה, chamulah, God is going to have great compassion. Because
of you, I will have compassion on them.
So what was הצית אש עליה hietit eish aleha then? Well, that's
a good point. I guess because it was הצית אש עליה, hietit
eish aleha, in response I will have great compassion, but yeah, that's
a good point.
אני אמרתי שישתעבדו בארבע מלכויות כל אחת ואחת כשיעור ארבע מלכויות. Ani
amarti sheyishta'adu b'arba malchuyos kol achas v'achas k'shiur arba malchuyos.
I said that they will have to be in subject to, you
know, the four kingdoms, this understanding about, all this goes back to
אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu and חז"ל Chazal tie in the vision that
he had with ברית בין הבתרים Bris Bein Habesarim to the different
four kingdoms which the Jewish people would be subject to. So I
said that they would all be that we be subject to like
a four kingdoms, the full length of what a kingdom means, you
know, hundreds of years, like it was with מצרים. Mitzrayim. So what
are the four kingdoms, by the way? They are מצרים, Mitzrayim, then
בבל, Bavel, which is the חורבן בית ראשון, Churban Beis Rishon,
then פרס ומדי, Paras uMadai, I forget if they count this as
one or two, then יון, Yavan, right, Greece, and then רומי. Romi.
So anyway, and רומי Romi is the one that we're currently under,
you know, חז"ל's Chazal's mind, רומי Romi becomes Christianity and we're still
under רומי. Romi. So anyway, not all of those were as long
as others. So as the גמרא Gemara says, so here's what God
is
saying, השתא כל חד וחד מאי דפסיק ליה, Hashta kol chad v'chad
mai d'pasik lei,
each one will be what sort of allotted to it each. You'll
be subject to these kingdoms, not in equal amount for each one.
So I'll be I'll go a little bit easier on them. איכא
דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, here's what God said, אני אמרתי בזה
וזה, Ani amarti b'zeh v'zeh, I said they'd have to serve, you
know, a... sequential sentences, the four kingdoms one after the other. עכשיו
בבת אחת, Achshav b'vas achas, now I am letting them serve one
minute simultaneous—what's it called? Concurrent sentences. So, you know, sometimes there'll be
some of the Jews will be under Greece and others will be
under Persia and therefore it'll there'll be some overlap between these four
kingdoms and it won't last as long as it otherwise would. Let's
just finish and then I'll take your question Bobby. אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi so Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
says למה נמשלו ישראל לזית lama nimshalu Yisrael l'zayis why are the
people of Israel compared to an olive tree which was earlier in
the פסוק pasuk as where we said like the good is kind
of come at the end לומר לך lomar l'cha to tell you
מה זית אין עליו נושרים לא בימות החמה ולא בימות הגשמים ma
zayis ein alav noshrim lo b'yamos hachamah v'lo b'yamos hageshamim
the same way an olive tree the leaves do not wither fall
off whether in the summer or in the rainy season in the
winter it's a perennial אף ישראל אין להם בטילה עולמית af Yisrael
ein lahem beteilah olamis so the Jewish people will never be destroyed
לא בעולם הזה ולא בעולם הבא lo b'olam hazeh v'lo b'olam haba
not in this world not in that world it's true we will
be you know oppressed and suffer and even have obviously you know
tremendous tragedies that occur but ultimately we will be we will continue
to survive whether in this world and certainly in the future world.
ואמר רבי יוחנן למה נמשלו ישראל לזית V'amar Rabbi Yochanan lama nimshalu
Yisrael l'zayis why are they compared to an olive tree לומר לך
lomar l'cha to tell you מה זית אינו מוציא שמנו אלא על
ידי כתישה ma zayis eino motzi shamno ela al yedei ketishah
the same way olives do not give off their oil except through
pounding אף ישראל אין חוזרים למוטב אלא על ידי ייסורים af Yisrael
ein chozrim l'mutav ela al yedei yissurim
so the Jewish people sometimes they can't get back on the right
path except when they suffer ultimately you know that sort of like
the מדרש Midrash that says about אחשורוש Achashveirosh when it says ויסר
טבעתו מעל ידו ויתנה להמן Vayasar taba'aso me'al yado vayitnah l'Haman
so this very powerful מדרש Midrash in מגילה Megillah says you know
all of the words of all of the hundreds of years of
all of the prophets could not do as much as that one
handing of the ring of אחשורוש Achashveirosh to המן. Haman. You know
so you know you could get yelled at and yelled at and
talked and talked and talked to but it's only when the tragedy
is hanging there that that'll sort of motivate you to do תשובה.
teshuvah. It's a sad way to end because you know that sort
of juxtaposition of we go it's sort of tried to end at
a consolation note oh you know yes it was terrible the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash was destroyed but we're always going to survive and
then רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan sort of pulls us back into reality.
Yeah we're going to survive but you know we gotta suffer as
a result that's part of our that's part of our life
as well.
Less compassionate God said to אברהם Avraham על חמלתי עליה al chamalti
aleha I have compassion on them I'm going to make them suffer?
Well I don't know if he's reading that back as God's response
or just sort of making this additional point that the comparison to
the זית zayis was that yes suffering will be part look that
is part of the ברית בין הבתרים Bris Bein Habesarim as well
you know is what Avra—yet there is this covenant and yet and
so on but there's also this you know it also involves suffering.
It's not right it's not a very cheery message it's a realistic
one. So it is it is funny sort of the way that
it end we were hoping it would end on a little softer
note and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan sort of jars us back a
little bit into reality.
Yeah definitely thinking about the Rifka?
Yes. It is compassionate if you compare it to total annihilation. Well
that's true exactly terrible comparison but better to live than—all right so
that was one thing but here when you were talking about the
four kingdom it was in addition to Egypt
oh okay fine so that's how account מדי Madai and Greece right
so that's how they get פרס Paras and מדי Madai separate ones
right. What do they have there Persia Media
Babylonia Media Persia Greece and Rome.
Babylonia Media right okay okay yeah yeah I had forgotten whether that
Egypt was counted as one of the four or not. Okay so
certainly then if you think about פרס Paras and מדי Madai separate
מדי Madai is very short it's a few years so that you
know explains that God is saying they don't all they're not all
going to be of equal length. Okay so that is the end
of that מדרש Midrash and we did point out some interesting characters
in the way tied in again and the to the de-emphasis or
ignoring of the whole זכות אבות zechus avos and אברהם Avraham praying
after the fact and so on. Okay so let's now move on
back to the halachic discussion. רבי מאיר אומר השאור בתוך המידה להחמיץ
בו ומחמיצן. Rabbi Meir omer hase'or b'soch hamidah l'hachmitz bo u'machmitzan. How
do you make those מנחות minchos that do come חמץ chametz not
offered on the altar but that they do come חמץ? chametz? How
do you bring them how do you how do you make them
חמץ? chametz? This would be the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem for שבועות
Shavuos most significantly but also the תודה. Todah. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says you take some of the flour from the measure you
make it dough you turn it into sourdough and you put it
back of course רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that's not going to
be very strong sourdough and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you take
your own sourdough and you add then flour to it. So let's
take a look. However the problem which רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
that then the measure is not the right amount because as the
גמרא Gemara says your sourdough will be either denser or less dense
than normal flour. So then if you just insert it and measure
the other flour with it you're not going to get the exact
right amount of flour. מה חסירה ויתירה Ma chaseira v'yeseira so that's
what the גמרא Gemara said. What does it mean that it'll be
too little or too much? Your measure. אמר רב חסדא עיסת שאור
עבה Amar Rav Chisda isas se'or avah if your dough is thick
dense נמצאת יתירה nimzas yeseira then it is taking up you know
the same amount of flour is taking up less space in this
sourdough. So then you add, you fill up the rest of the
container, you're gonna in the end have more flour because you've compressed
a certain area of it where you have your sourdough, more flour
than you normally would. מדת עשרון רכה נמצאת יתירה מדת עשרון. Midat
isaron raka nimses yeseira midat isaron. Then the amount of the, then
the עשרון isaron you'll have more flour than usual. רכה, Raka, if
it is too loose, less dense than flour, נמצאת חסירה, nimses chaseira,
then you won't have the normal, you won't have the right amount.
So the גמרא Gemara says דוק דוק כי קהלי סולת קהלי. dok
dok ki kahaly solet kahaly. So גמרא Gemara says what do I
care? Right now when you're measuring, you have, you fill the measure.
So who cares if part of it is sourdough and part of
it is flour? Let's just look at what we have in front
of us and it exactly fills the measure. So רבה ורב יוסף
דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabba veRav Yosef damrei tarvaihu, רבה Rabba and רב יוסף
Rav Yosef both say לכמות שהן היו משערינן. likmosei shehein hayu mesharinan.
You measure it not the way it is now but the way
it should have been in the past. So when the תורה Torah
says that you take an עשרון isaron of flour, and the תורה
Torah explicitly says עשרון סולת, isaron solet, it doesn't say an עשרון
isaron of dough, it says an עשרון isaron of flour. So you
have to measure it at how much is as the flour that
goes an עשרון isaron's worth of flour. So even if right now
it fills the עשרון, isaron, if there's more flour or less flour
than the עשרון, isaron, that's a problem. So if the density has
changed because of this pocket of sourdough, that's a problem. So we
go by the amount of flour, not by what you have in
front of you.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, oh wait, I got a solution.
דלישקול פורתא מיניה וליחמציה מאבראי וליסיבי ולינחה בהדיה. delishkol porta minei velichmasei
me'ivrai velisyevei velincha bahadei. The גמרא Gemara says I've got a great
suggestion. Now read one way this sounds to be exactly what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says. It says why don't you measure out the
amount, take a certain amount out, take a certain amount of flour
out, make it into dough outside of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
let it become sourdough and then bring it back in. Okay, now
that's exactly basically what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says you take a certain amount of flour from it, make
it sourdough, bring it back in. Maybe the גמרא Gemara's saying is
that do that over a longer period of time, you know, really
make it, you know, have it last for a long period of
time for a couple of years and so you get good sourdough,
then bring it back in. Of course you have to plan ahead
because who knows how much, you know, because I'm trying to bring
my מנחה. mincha. The other way רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos say
what this could mean is why not run a test? Why not
see how much flour goes into this density of dough and then
you'll be able to approximate, you know, sort of figure out how
much flour goes into the עשרון, isaron, you know, why not let
sort of run a test? Okay. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says no,
גזירה דילמא אתי לאשוויי מעלמא. gzeira dilma asi lashvuyei mealma. If you
did that, you did something outside and then you brought it back
in and you measured it again, so however you did it, people
are going to think that you know that you can add the
sourdough to the measure and they won't realize that the sourdough that
you're using have to constitute a part of the measure. So therefore
we don't like this idea of taking it out, you have to
measure it all together. So according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, actually
yes, what you do is you do take part of the flour
and you make it sourdough but you do that pretty quickly, and
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you take sourdough but then you
measure it all together, you don't somehow do this which is first
measure it, then take it out, then put it back in. If
you first measured it and now you're coming and you're dropping the
sourdough back in without measuring it all together, it looks like you're
adding stuff that has not been measured. It looks like first you
make the measure and then you can add the sourdough afterwards which
is not the case. Okay, so either you take the flour, you
measure it, you take the flour and then you make the sourdough
from that flour, or you go ahead you put in a sourdough
and then you fill up the measure with the rest of flour.
All right, very good. So that is the debate about how to
make חמץ. chametz. Like I said, it's refreshing to be talking a
little bit about how to make how to make חמץ chametz rather
than how to prevent חמץ, chametz, okay? But that's only at a
few מנחות. minchos. The basic rule is that all the מנחות minchos
have to be מצה matzah and even these מנחות minchos that are
חמץ, chametz, if you offer it up on the מזבח mizbayach as
חמץ chametz then you know you transgress. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אין
מחמיצין בתפוחים. Ein machmisin betapuchim. You cannot use apple juice for making
חמץ. chametz. Now
here you're trying to make חמץ, chametz, but the same is true
in the reverse. Okay, so if you're trying to make the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem out of חמץ, chametz, you cannot use apple juice.
Okay, because you need water. This is a principle of מי פירות
אין מחמיצין. Mei peirot ein machmisin.
That other liquids, juices, also there's an issue about egg and egg
מצות matzos do not create חמץ. chametz. You need water to create
חמץ. chametz. I'll talk about the implications about this in a minute,
let's first see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so משום רבי
חנינא בן גמליאל אמרו, mishum Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel amru, in the
name of רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel they said,
תפוחים, Tapuchim, 94a, מחמיצין. machmisin. No, apple juice can make חמץ chametz
so you can use that in this מנחה. mincha. And of course,
the funny thing
is even if it's true that you can make חמץ chametz out
of it, who allowed you to bring in this external ingredient? Right?
Who ever said? I mean the תורה Torah says that you have
oil and flour, it doesn't even say water, which I'll discuss in
a minute, but let's even say it could create חמץ chametz out
of out of apple juice. Since when am I allowed to bring
in apple juice? That's not one of the ingredients. Presumably, the understanding
is since you have to make it חמץ, chametz, so maybe in
this as part of making it חמץ, chametz, since that's what the
תורה Torah demands, then you have that latitude to choose. to use
this ingredient. Although it is quite interesting. But let's also remember that
the תורה Torah does not even mention flour either, water either, and
presumably you are using water. I'll get back to that in a
minute. Let's first see this debate. רב כהנא Rav Kahana מתני masni
לה lah רבי חנינא בן תרדיון. Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon. רב כהנא
Rav Kahana says it wasn't רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi Chanina ben
Gamliel who said that apple juice creates חמץ, chametz, it was רבי
חנינא בן תרדיון. Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon. Okay. Now we're going to
see if we can prove who the, you know, one side. כמאן
אזלא הא דתנן, Keman azla ha detnan, how about this משנה mishna
in תרומות Trumos that says the following:
תפוח שריסקו ונתנו בתוך העיסה וחימצה. tapuach sherisko unetano betoch haisa vekimtza.
You have an apple that you chopped up and you, you know,
you basically mushed. That's a technical term. And then you put it
into your flour. Okay to make, now, what now, relevant is here
is this apple is תרומה. truma. תרומה, Truma, you mixed it up
with other things, it could become בטל, battel, like anything else can
become בטל, battel, its identity can be nullified. However, one way in
which תרומה truma does not become בטל battel is if it causes
the dough to ferment. Then its impact is felt. So if you
have a little sourdough of תרומה, truma, even a little bit, and
put it in a lot of other dough, the תרומה truma is
not בטל, battel, it's not nullified because it caused the whole thing
to, you know,
to ferment and to rot. To leaven. Right. So let's say what
you put in was a crushed apple of תרומה. truma. Would that
be considered...
see, and then it's...
it doesn't. That's why you have to know context. If you look
at the side on the right hand column, תרומות פרק ג משנה
ב. Trumos perek gimmel mishna bet. You see that that's where we're
getting the משנה mishna from. Okay, but you know, that's why you,
why you have רש"י Rashi or, why, you know, the גמרא, Gemara,
if it knew its material it knew where the context of where
it's quoting something, but it doesn't always help us by telling us
that. Okay, so this is a case of תרומה. truma. And the
question here is, is it בטל battel or not? And is what
is what the apple juice is doing to the yeast considered causing
it to ferment, being מחמיץ, machmitz, as a way that it will
prevent ביטול? bittul? And therefore you'll still have תרומה truma here? So
it says like this: הרי
זו אסורה. harei zo asura. It is forbidden, meaning it's still considered
תרומה truma because the apple is still considered to be present. So
you see apple juice causes fermentation and apple juice is מחמיץ. machmitz.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says: חזי chazi going like that
apple juice is מחמיץ? machmitz? כמאן? Keman? Who is that going like?
לימא רבי חנינא בן גמליאל? Lema Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel? Let's say
it's רבי חנינא בן גמליאל, Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel, who similarly says
that apple juice is מחמיץ machmitz for the
מנחה, mincha, ולא רבנן, velo Rabbanan, and not the רבנן. Rabbanan. So
the גמרא Gemara says: no, אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu tema Rabbanan, even
the רבנן Rabbanan who say you cannot use apple juice for a
מנחה mincha say that it would be a problem by תרומה. truma.
Why? ניהי דחמץ גמור לא הוי נוקשא מיהא הוי. Nihi dechametz gamur
lo havei nuksha miha havei. It might be true that it's not
חמץ גמור chametz gamur and therefore they don't want you to use
it for your מנחה, mincha, but it might be... remember yesterday we
had that idea of quasi-חמץ, chametz, the space between being real leaven
and being מצה. matza. And therefore that would be enough to be
a problem by תרומה. truma. Okay, so now there are a couple
of issues that come up here. Issue number one is when the
תורה Torah says certain things have to be... when it can't be
חמץ, chametz, we discussed yesterday that that as... when it has to
be מצה, matza, we discussed yesterday that it can't be in this
middle quasi-חמץ chametz category. Okay, this חמץ נוקשא, chametz nuksha, quasi-חמץ, chametz,
you know, where it starts sort of the, the crust starts to
hardening and so on. It has to be real מצה. matza. But
how about the opposite? How about when it's supposed to be חמץ?
chametz? Like the
תודה, toda, the bread of the תודה, toda, the שתי הלחם? shtei
halechem? Does it have to be full חמץ chametz that you would
get כרת kares for if you had it on פסח? Pesach? 100%
חמץ, chametz, or can it even be this quasi, this חמץ נוקשא?
chametz nuksha? So that is, you know, that here the גמרא Gemara
is saying is might exactly might be the, you know, the רבנן
Rabbanan's position. The רבנן Rabbanan say I'm not denying it's חמץ נוקשא,
chametz nuksha, I'm just saying that you can't use it for a
מנחה. mincha. There you need חמץ, chametz, you need real חמץ. chametz.
The same way presumably if you need מצה, matza, you need 100%
מצה. matza. If you need חמץ, chametz, you need 100% חמץ chametz
and not quasi-חמץ. chametz. That's one question: what is the definition of
מצה matza and what's the definition of חמץ chametz for a מנחה,
mincha, because we've now found out that there's a middle category. Okay,
but the other interesting issue is that the fruit juices don't create
real חמץ. chametz. And there's a huge תוספות Tosfos here and there's
תוספות Tosfos in פסחים Psachim as well, which is that really true?
There are other גמרות Gemaros that seem the opposite extreme. Some גמרות
Gemaros that seem that מי פירות mei peiros causes real חמץ, chametz,
like חמץ chametz to be חייב כרת chayav kares on פסח. Pesach.
Presumably that's רבי חנינא בן גמליאל. Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel. If he
says you can use it for the תודה toda and for the
מנחה mincha that requires חמץ, chametz, presumably he holds that fruit juices
cause real חמץ. chametz. On the other hand, there are other גמרות
Gemaros that sound like fruit juices are complete non-problem. That it's not
even a רבנן rabbinic problem and you can totally have, you know,
fruit juices and flour, you know, type of an egg מצה matza
and so on on פסח Pesach and it won't become חמץ chametz
even if you leave it out. Okay, so what's the story? So
תוספות Tosfos tries to figure it all out. This is why there's
all these questions about eating egg מצה matza on פסח. Pesach. תוספות
Tosfos's general conclusion, although he goes back and forth on it, is
the following: is that if you don't use other water, you only
use fruit juices, that then it will, it will not become חמץ.
chametz.
And
and therefore, or maybe at most חמץ נוקשא, chametz nuksha, but anyway
it'll certainly never become real חמץ chametz if it's only, if it's
without water. And according to that you could You could eat it
on פסח *Pesach*. You might even be able to eat it without,
even if you let it sit out for a while before baking
it. That's at least what leads to the discussions in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* like here where it comes up quasi-חמץ *chametz* or according
to רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina* maybe full חמץ *chametz*. And there's another
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that says if you use fruit juices you have
to be extra careful because then it might become חמץ *chametz* even
quicker. That's when there's fruit juices plus water. Okay, so that basically
תוספות'ס *Tosafot's* approach. Other ראשונים *Rishonim* disagree, but תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says
without water it will never become חמץ *chametz*. Where it comes quasi
or full חמץ *chametz* or maybe even quicker חמץ *chametz* than normal
thing, that's when it's juices with water. The מנהג *minhag* not to
eat egg מצה *matzah* on פסח *Pesach* except for people that are
like sick and so on, you know that came up because there
was because there is a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that says that fruit
juices cause it to become חמץ *chametz* quicker even acknowledging that תוספות
*Tosafot* says it only means when there is water but that's not
the only way to read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* might be that even without water fruit juices create חמץ *chametz*
and create it even quicker than water. So if fruit juices can
create חמץ *chametz* quicker than water, so you don't want to be
eating egg מצה *matzah* or you know apple juice מצה *matzah* on
פסח *Pesach* because there's even a greater chance that they're חמץ *chametz*.
And that's where that מנהג *minhag* comes from. But at least according
to תוספות *Tosafot* those concerns of חמץ *chametz* are only with the
addition of water. So that's in terms of fruit juices. Now it's
too bad that Michael isn't here, people will have to report to
him because Michael has always been very concerned legitimately with the question
of:
did
you use water in the making of a מנחה Mincha, *mincha*? Okay?
The תורה *Torah* never says water, it says oil, okay, which is
a fruit juice, right? I mean we don't think about it but
it's not water, it's something that's extracted from a fruit.
Yeah, right. So anyway did you use water? Because if you didn't
use water, right, so then we're finding out here at least according
to the רבנן *Rabbanan* that מי פירות אינם מחמיצים *mei peirot einam
machmitzim* and according to תוספות *Tosafot* everybody would say without water you're
never going to become חמץ *chametz*. So what's the תורה's *Torah's* concern
of חמץ *chametz* on the one hand? And on the other hand
if you didn't use water, now maybe the תורה's *Torah's* concern is
don't add water and don't make it חמץ *chametz*. But let's ask
it on the flip: those מנחות *minchot* that are supposed to be
חמץ *chametz*, right? How do they get חמץ *chametz* if you didn't
use water if you only used oil? So here a later משנה
Mishnah? *Mishna* says that what we'll see it in about two days
so I won't turn to it now because but later משנה Mishnah
*Mishna* basically says, you know, that talks about says כל המנחות נילושות
בפושרים *kol
haminchot niloshot beposhrim*, with lukewarm water. So basically says that you use
water with all the מנחות *minchot*. And then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says oh but one minute the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says what about
the מנחת נסכים *minchat nesachim*, right, the ones that came with the
קרבנות *korbanot*. It says there there was no water so how is
it possible for it to become חמץ *chametz*? This is what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says and then gets into a discussion again about
מי פירות *mei peirot* and חמץ *chametz*. So תוספות *Tosafot* says well
why all of a sudden are we assuming there was no water
with the מנחת נסכים *minchat nesachim* but we were assuming there was
water, right, with the other מנחות *minchot*? So תוספות *Tosafot* says well
the מנחת נסכים *minchat nesachim*, if you might remember from a few
days ago, had a lot more oil mixed into the flour. So
תוספות *Tosafot* is saying maybe we assume that since there's so much
oil that we're using the oil instead of the water, okay, we're
using the oil instead of the water and therefore we're assuming that
you don't need to use water in the actual kneading, you're just
using oil. And then the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* still saying but okay
but it can't become חמץ *chametz*. So according to תוספות *Tosafot* the
way he reads that גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* which is simple way of
reading it, all the מנחות *minchot* had water which had the potential
of becoming חמץ *chametz* and some had to be חמץ *chametz* with
the one exception of the מנחת נסכים *minchat nesachim*, right, that it
had so much oil that it did not, you know, that they
didn't necessarily need water and that maybe didn't have the possibility of
becoming חמץ *chametz*. That's the way תוספות *Tosafot* reads that and it
makes sense because if you need water, מי פירות אינם מחמיצים *mei
peirot einam machmitzim*, whatever, you need water, how do you have the
whole חמץ *chametz* discussion? The רמב"ם *Rambam* says differently. The רמב"ם *Rambam*
says very much, he re-reads that משנה Mishnah *Mishna* and he says
not כל המנחות נילושות בפושרים *kol haminchot niloshot beposhrim* but the רמב"ם
*Rambam* says כל המנחות הנאפות נילושות בפושרים *kol haminchot hane'afot niloshot beposhrim*,
that מנחות *minchot* that you're going to bake, right, think about some
מנחות *minchot* were basically made, you know, as like how, you know,
basically it's like oil and there's got to be a word for
this dish, it's basically fried flour, like it's oil and flour and
you fry it.
Okay, what? תודה *Toda*, תודה *Toda*?
You bake it and then you fry it? But he says that's
not, you know, that's not baking and there's no possibility there of
חמץ *chametz* and therefore you don't need water there. So according to
the רמב"ם *Rambam* the only place that you have water in a
מנחה Mincha *mincha* is when it talks about making it a type
of a bread. Now there are two types of bread, there's leavened
and unleavened. So the מנחות *minchot* that come מצה *matzah*, you have
the baked ones you have water but you don't let it rise,
and the ones that are חמץ *chametz* like the שתי הלחם *Shtei
Halechem* you have water and you do let it rise or use
sourdough like we're being taught. But the upshot is according to the
רמב"ם *Rambam* the only place you introduce water which is not an
ingredient in the תורה *Torah* is when it's in a context of
making bread. And therefore in that context you could talk about it
has to be מצה *matzah* bread or it has to be חמץ
*chametz* bread. But those are two variations of bread and that's where
water is significant. So the important thing to get from this גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* is all of a sudden we're discovering
that
מי פירות *mei peirot* are According to תוספות *Tosafot* everybody would agree
that that was without water. And now we can ask so what's
the whole issue about חמץ *chametz* versus מצה *matzah* by the מנחות
*minchas*? Where is there water? And the גמרא *Gemara* basically introduces water
into one of the ingredients according to תוספות *Tosafot* introduces it into
all of the מנחות *minchas*, according to the רמב"ם *Rambam* it introduces
it only into the baked מנחות *minchas* of which there were מצה
*matzah* types and there were חמץ *chametz* types. We're talking now about
the חמץ *chametz* types, about the שתי הלחם *Shtei HaLechem*.
Does anyone explain why the water wouldn't be mentioned?
Well, it is mentioned in a later משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*.
Not mentioned here,
yeah, maybe taking it for granted. If it's talking about making it
מאפה תנור *mafeh tanur* baking, you can't bake flour. Flour is mentioned.
I know, I don't know, but the תורה *Torah* isn't specifying a
certain שיעור shiur *shiur*. You know, it's sort of like a necessary
thing in order to make it work but not as something that's
of- being offered. You offer your flour to God, you're offering your
oil to God, you're not offering your water to God. You have
to put the water in in order to make it into a
מנחה Mincha *minchah* but it's not like part of what's being offered.
But we still don't know how much water though. Well, we don't,
and actually from the גמרא *Gemara* before that talked about loose sourdough
or dense sourdough, presumably you have a latitude in terms of that
as well. Okay, so now we continue.
Okay, okay, okay. The water's given by God, this is from
him.
Well, everything is given by God but often water is not feels-
something that you have produced that you now want to give back
to God. But the amount is not set. Okay, it's in order
to make it into bread however much you need you judge. Okay,
so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אמר רב Rav, אילא
*Amar Rav Ila*, so רב אילא *Rav Ila* said, אין לך קשה
לקמיצה יותר ממנחת חוטא *ein lecha kasheh likmitzah yoter miminchat chote*. There
is nothing harder to do קמיצה k'mitzah. *kmitzah* on than a מנחה
Mincha, *minchah* of a sinner because the מנחה *minchah* that's- serves as
a type of a חטאת *chatat*, which is in a few examples
you're allowed to bring a מנחה *minchah* type of a variable-cost חטאת
*chatat*, so it's there's nothing on it, just plain flour. So the
problem is לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה *lo yasim
aleha shemen velo yiten aleha levonah* because I think כי חטאת היא
*ki chatat hi*.
You're thinking מנחת קנאות *minchat kna'ot*. I was thinking מנחת קנאות *minchat
kna'ot* is what I was thinking. Okay, but the other one anyway
is
still- still also no flour- no- no oil and no לבונה *levonah*.
So it's a מנחת חוטא Minchas Chotei *minchat chote*. So imagine you
had a bag of flour and you tried to take the קמיצה
*kmitzah* from it, right? So little things are- you're not going to
get an exact amount. It's hard to hold on to that full
amount, stuff will spill out. If it's with- if it's kneaded, if
it's got oil mixed into it, so it's easier to get an
amount and to hold on for it. But this way it's hard
to hold well- let's see what the גמרא *Gemara* says. Okay, hold
on. This is the מנחת חוטא Minchas Chotei. *minchat chote* remember, so
it's only flour. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. רב יצחק
בר אבדימי אמר מנחת חוטא מגבלה במים וכשרה *Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi
amar minchat chote megablah bemayim uksherah*. I got a solution, just add
some water to it. Okay, it could still be כשרה *ksherah* with
water and therefore, and that'll hold it together and make it easier
to do the קמיצה *kmitzah*. Now again what's fascinating is, you know,
the idea that you're allowed to insert extraneous ingredients sort of like
the גמרא *Gemara* before almost just glossed over it about the discussion
of apple juice. You know, why don't we say that any extraneous
ingredient makes it a different object? Now I'm not saying that but
of course even if you say it's not a different object you
could ask what allows you to be מקריב *makriv* that extra ingredient
on the מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbe'ach*. Isn't that a type of חולין בעזרה
*chullin ba'azarah*? Meaning let's say I don't know, let's say I you
know put some you know pinned some I don't know flowers on
my- I can't even think what the example would be. But let-
whatever let's say I- ביכורים *bikkurim* you decided to put some something
else. Whatever, exactly. Let's say I did a little sprinkling of cinnamon
on top of my מנחה *minchah*.
Okay so even- so even if you
say it doesn't make it פסול *pasul*, am I allowed to now
be מקריב *makriv* it on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*? Isn't that a type
of חולין בעזרה *chullin ba'azarah*? The גמרא *Gemara* seems to be unconcerned
with that, maybe because it's incidental, it's not your focus. Anyway, so
add some water, that'll solve your problem. Now Michael says what about
didn't we just say that all the מנחות *minchas* had water? Sure,
all the מנחות *minchas* that weren't מנחת חוטא *minchat chote*. מנחת חוטא
*minchat chote* is just flour. Everything else is some mixture of liquid
with the flour and some sort of cooking that's going on. This
is just the flour.
So you would be also with the מנחת סוטה *minchat sotah* too?
Because you know- right, exactly, so everything else according to תוספות *Tosafot*
had water.
Right. Exactly. So the גמרא *Gemara* says וכשרה *uksherah*. So I'm sorry,
מגבלה במים וכשרה *megablah bemayim uksherah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says למימר
בהא קמיפלגי *leimar beha ka mipalgi*. So obviously רב אילא *Rav Ila*
did not hold of that position. So let's say this is what
they're arguing about. מר סבר Mar savar כמות שהן kemot shehen משערינן
ומר סבר כמות שהיו משערינן *mar savar kemot shehen mishari-nin umar savar
kemot shehayu mishari-nin*. One says you measure it the way they are
and one says you measure it the way they were. Meaning when
you have to get that עשרון issaron. *issaron* of flour, right, if
you're measuring it based on- so if you're measuring it now, so
what you do, you've added water and now you're going to take
the measure. Well, the problem is now you're taking the measure with
the water, you're not getting the right עשרון issaron. *issaron* of flour.
There's a different amount here. So one will say oh it's okay,
you can measure based on what you have in front of you.
And the other says no, no, no, you need to measure based
on the original amount of flour. Now it's particularly bizarre to think
you're allowed to measure based on the amount in front of you
when you've added an extraneous ingredient. It's one thing to say before
when you've made sourdough if you understand that sourdough was a requisite
part of the process and so on. Here you've added an extraneous
ingredient and the גמרא *Gemara* is still saying oh maybe we can
go ahead and measure based on the amount in front of you.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says that's not really the debate. גמרא *Gemara*
says לא *lo*. No, that's not the debate. דכולי עלמא כמות שהן
kemot shehen משערינן *dechulei alma kemot shehen mishari-nin*. Everybody would agree, interesting
way the גמרא *Gemara* comes down here, you measure based on what's
in front of you, which is fascinating based on what we said
before, it sounds like- it sounded like everybody said you measure based
on what it used to be. But again if we rule like
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that says you can take the sourdough from
your home and fill up the amount with the requisite amount of
flour after, so רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is saying you can base
on what you're dealing with right now. You don't have to worry,
oh is how much flour went into this sourdough. You do based
on what's in front of you right now. So that's what the
גמרא's saying. It's taking רבי יהודה's position. You measure based on what's
in front of you right now. Again what's quite fascinating is the
assumption you could even do it when you have this additional ingredient
of water, which was not sort of dictated that you can measure
based on what's in front of you right now. So then if
that's true, what's the debate? Here's the debate. It has nothing to
do with the right amount of flour. Here's the debate.
ובהא קמיפלגי. U'veha kamiflegi. Here's the debate. דמר סבר חריבה חריבה משמן.
Demar savar chareiva chareiva mishemen. When the Torah says that a מנחה,
this מנחה has to be a desolate, like it has to be
dry. Dry means no oil. ומר סבר חריבה מכל דבר. Umar savar
chareiva mikol davar. No, it has to be dry from everything. You're
not allowed to use water. So the debate is whether the Torah
has forbidden water as an ingredient, does that make it no longer
חריבה? chareiva? And that's what they're debating. It's a simple question. If
the Torah says dry, are you allowed to add water? If the
answer is yes, then you add water as a way of solving
how to do the קמיצה. Okay, and then also you can measure
based on how much it fills up right now with the water
in it.
And then also they call them the מנחת חריבה? Minchas Chareiva?
Yeah. Well, the Torah refers to it as, you know, וכל מנחה
V'chol mincha reshifei, what's the פסוק? pasuk?
I forgot what the פסוק... pasuk... where, where... oh, מנחת חוטא is
right here.
וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן וחריבה, V'chol mincha belula vashemen vachareiva,
so it doesn't specifically say חריבה, chareiva, but it says there is
a חריבה chareiva and we assume that's talking about a מנחת חוטא.
So again what's quite fascinating here is that the simple addition of
some ingredient does not invalidate. The only reason it would invalidate is
because the Torah explicitly describes it as dry. But had the Torah
not said that, the addition of some ingredient would not per se
invalidate and it's not per se a problem to put it on
the מזבח. And again that's alluded to before with the גמרא's discussion
about the apple juice, but it's surprising. And you know, maybe this
goes into the idea that a מנחה is this one קרבן Korban
that is actually constructed. You know, it is, and therefore maybe, you
know, interestingly maybe allows for a certain tolerance for other ingredients. Okay,
with the exception of this that's a חריבה, chareiva, yeah.
Now, you know,
it seems like getting precisely an עשרון. issaron But like, you know,
so you put in an עשרון. I mean like, you know, but
it's not exactly smooth. They really take a thing and smooth it
out.
They'll talk about that later, about how exactly you measure.
There'll be a discussion. And even if it doesn't have to be
exact, okay, so you can do it within a certain tolerance, you
know, but it doesn't mean that you want to really, you want
to go beyond that tolerance level, which is the concern here. Okay.
תנן התם. Tnan hasam. So we taught over there. Now we're going
to have a more general question, not about a מנחה, but in
general when things change, do you measure them based on their current
way they present themselves or the way they were originally? I'll just
say as an introductory thing, this is not going to have anything
to do with flour
and dough and so on. It has to do with like pieces
of meat that get bigger or smaller and how much creates טומאה
tumah and doesn't create טומאה tumah if it's of a dead animal
etc. And תוספות points out that whatever you say over there, it's
not logically the same as what we're saying here because here the
Torah says עשרון סולת. issaron soles. The Torah explicitly says take an
עשרון of flour. It's like you have your ingredients in a recipe,
right? And if it says take two cups of flour, the point
is I said two cups of flour, not two cups of dough,
right? This is the recipe. We're talking about the ingredient here. So
the logic here to say that you go by the original amount
of flour is very compelling. That's what the Torah says. It doesn't
mean in other places we would go by, you know, the original
as opposed to how it's presenting itself right now. Okay, but this
is how the גמרא is going to discuss. Let's take a look.
So תנן התם. Tnan hasam. We taught over there in עוקצין, Uktzin,
which is a מסכת masechet about טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. בשר העגל,
Basar ha'eigel, if you have meat of a calf, a dead calf,
and you have meat, and you need a כביצה k'beitzah worth of
the meat of a dead animal or normally of types of טומאה
tumah to transfer the טומאה tumah to another object. So you have
this meat of a dead calf and it is, the question is
is it a כביצה, k'beitzah, the size of an egg or not?
So שנתפח, She'nitpach, that
it expanded. It used to be less than an egg but if
it was left around and it bloated a little bit, right. And
apparently רש"י Rashi says that's what happens to the meat of a
calf.
ובשר זקינה, U'vesar zekeinah, and now our alternative, you have a meat
of an old animal, an aged animal, and there if you leave
it around it'll shrivel a little bit. So it started the right
price, כביצה, k'beitzah, but now שנתמעך, she'nitmaeich, now it has so much
shriveled. So do you measure the amount of size for טומאה tumah
based on what it originally was or based on what it is
right now? So it says: משערין לכמות שהן. Mishtarin l'chamosh shehen. You
measure it based on the way that they were. Now of course
we're going to have, so let's take a look.
Wait, no, לכמות שהן, l'chamosh shehen, that they mean the way they
are. Now we're going to have two אמוראים, Amoraim, groups of אמוראים
Amoraim debating how to read that phrase or what the גרסא girsa
was. Let's take a look.
Wait on the first one though...
No, it was
started as less than a בית סאה, beis sa'ah, now it's a
בית סאה. beis sa'ah. Oh, okay. So רב, רבי חייא, Rebbe Chiya,
and רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan, this group of אמוראים Amora'im אמרי משתערין
כמות שהן. amri mishta'arin kemot shehen. You measure based on the way
it is right now. שמואל ורבי שמעון ברבי וריש לקיש, Shmuel v'Rebbe
Shimon b'Rebbi v'Reish Lakish, this other group of
אמוראים Amora'im אמרי amri they say משתערין לכמות, mishta'arin l'kemot, you see
a little אלף, aleph, which switches it to לכמות שהיו, l'kemot shehayu,
or of course saying the exact same thing, you go by the
way it used to be. However, I will say that if you
I believe this is correct, if you read the גמרא carefully, they
make a distinction with כמות שהן as opposed to לכמות שהן. l'kemot
shehen. כמות שהן is the way it is right now. לכמות שהן
l'kemot shehen means toward how it was, usually the למד lamed is
pointing you away the way it used to be. But of course
that the difference between with the למד lamed and without the למד
lamed is a little too subtle, and it's much clearer to us
if the text is לכמות שהיו, l'kemot shehayu, the way it used
to be. So versus what you have there they pretty they re-
they changed the text here to make it clearer or maybe there
was some original text to be לכמות שהיו, l'kemot shehayu, but that's
a debate. How do you read this line in the משנה? Mishnah
Is it in the way it is now you assess, or you
assess the way it used to be? So the משנה Mishnah: seems
to give a ruling but the but the ruling is open was
it based on the text you have of that משנה it's open
for interpretation. So let's take a look. מתיבי, Mativei, I'll ask you
on this: בשר העגל שלא היה בו כשיעור. basar ha'eigel shelo haya
bo kishiur. וטפח. v'taphach. So we have a ברייתא braisa which is
very explicit. You have the flesh of a calf that did not
have the right size, it was less than a כביצה, kabeisa, and
it sort of bloated, it blew it expanded, ואמרה כשיעור, v'amra kishiur,
and now it's the size of a כביצה. kabeisa. טהור לשעבר וטמא
מכאן ולהבא. tahor l'sha'avar v'tamei mikan ulaba.
So from what happened till now it was טהור, tahor, it wasn't
the right size, anything it touched would not abstract to טומאה. tumah.
From here on in it causes טומאה tumah because now it's the
right size. So you see you go by what you have in
front of you and it's going to create טומאה. tumah. So he
said, no, מדרבנן. mi'derabbanan. That's Rabbinic. Okay, but how do you read
this? ואמרה כשיעור v'amra kishiur טהור tahor ואמרת v'amarta k'dei now it's
a כביצה, kabeisa, טהור לשעבר, tahor l'sha'avar,
in the past טהור, tahor, and now it's טמא tamei because it's
the size to create טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא says that's only
מדרבנן. mi'derabbanan. דאורייתא d'oraisa you would go by what it is by
what it was and it would never create טומאה tumah now because
it always started smaller, but we can be strict מדרבנן mi'derabbanan and
say now if it grew, it's going to create טומאה. tumah. So
the גמרא says one minute. אי הכי אימא סיפא, ei hachi eima
seifa, let's look at the end of that ברייתא. braisa. וכן בפיגול
וכן בנותר. v'chein b'pigul v'chein b'nosar. It says the same would be
true about פיגול ונותר. pigul v'nosar. Our good friends פיגול ונותר, pigul
v'nosar, right, leftover meat of a קרבן korban or a קרבן korban
that you had thought about eating it later and if you eat
a sized the requisite size, a כזית, kezayis, you would then get
כרת. kareis. So here it says that if it started less and
now it blew up and now you ate it, you're חייב. chayav.
Now we never say you're חייב chayav or you get כרת kareis
for Rabbinic. We could say it's אסור, assur, but we wouldn't say
you're חייב chayav and you get כרת. kareis. So how could this
just be a Rabbinic principle if we're applying it to פיגול ונותר?
pigul v'nosar? So אי אמרת בשלמא דאורייתא, ee amart b'shlama d'oraisa, if
it's a דאורייתא d'oraisa principle that you go by the size it
is right now, היינו דאיכא פיגול ונותר, haynu deika pigul v'nosar, therefore
there's a relevance of פיגול ונותר pigul v'nosar that you're חייב. chayav.
אלא אי אמרת דרבנן, ella ee amart d'rabbanan, if you're saying it's
a Rabbinic principle that you look at its current size, פיגול ונותר
בדרבנן מי איכא, pigul v'nosar b'rabbanan mi eeka, where do you have
that concept? I mean you could say it's אסור, assur, but when
we say פיגול ונותר, pigul v'nosar, that means that you're actually חייב
chayav for transgressing.
Why actually it's דאורייתא? d'oraisa?
Because this is the opinion that says that דאורייתא d'oraisa you go
by what it used to be. We're trying to prove the debate
and here it says look isn't it clear you go by what
it is? So we're trying to defend the side that argues you
go on what it used to be. So the גמרא says,
no, מי איכא mi ee- so אימא, eima, so it doesn't mean
eating פיגול ונותר, pigul v'nosar, אימא וכן בטומאת פיגול וכן בטומאת נותר,
eima v'chein b'tumath pigul v'chein b'tumath nosar, which anyway makes more sense
in context. פיגול pig- if you actually left meat of a קרבן
korban over and it became נותר, nosar, you had a thought on
the קרבן korban as פיגול pigul and it became פיגול, pigul, the
הלכה halacha is that that meat creates טומאה. tumah. Now normally you
don't say that, normally meat only creates טומאה tumah if it was
slaughtered incorrectly, it's a נבלה neveilah or something else touched it that
was טמא. tamei. But here the Rabbi said that since it is
now it's become invalid as a קרבן korban and it's נותר nosar
it's פיגול pigul there's other reasons as well about כהנים kohanim being
careful, it now has a Rabbinic טומאה. tumah. Okay so when we're
saying it's true by פיגול ונותר pigul v'nosar we don't mean eating
פיגול ונותר, pigul v'nosar, we mean פיגול ונותר pigul v'nosar as the
source of טומאה. tumah. Okay so if this started less than a
כביצה kabeisa and now it grew to a כביצה kabeisa and it's
פיגול pigul or נותר, nosar, it will create this Rabbinic טומאה tumah
and it's exactly the same rule. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina,
I would have thought, הואיל וטומאת פיגול וטומאת נותר דרבנן היא, ho
v'tumath pigul v'tumath nosar derabbanan hee, since the טומאה tumah created by
פיגול ונותר pigul v'nosar is only Rabbinic, כולי האי בדרבנן לא עביד
רבנן, kulei hai b'derabbanan lo avid rabbanan,
to make on a Rabbinic טומאה tumah another Rabbinic ruling that if
it grew in size we go by the current size, that would
be too much and we wouldn't do it, קא משמע לן kamashma
lan that we will do it. Okay so now we have the
idea that it's an explicit ברייתא braisa you go by the current
size, but we're trying to say that's only a Rabbinic stringency that
really you go by the original size. Now, but we're not done.
תא שמע, ta shma, let's look on the other side it's like
a it's like a קולא kula because if it was right well
that's what we're about to look at. תא שמע, ta shma, בשר
זקנה שהיה בו כשיעור. basar zekeina shehaya bo kishiur. So we have
a ברייתא braisa that's very explicit about the other way if you
have the meat of an old of an old animal which will
shrink and it started as a כביצה ke-betzah וצמק ve-tzamak and it
shrunk shriveled פחות מכשיעור pachot mikeshiur and now it is less טמא
לשעבר tamei le-she'avar so in the past it caused טומאה tumah because
in the past it was the right size and now וטהור מכאן
ולהבא ve-tahor mikan ve-haba from here on in it is טהור. tahor.
So this is quite explicit, you go by its current size right
and therefore and here it is even being lenient. It started the
right size, it shrunk, we're going to be lenient, we're going to
go by the current size, so you can't you have to admit
that this is not a rabbinic stringency, it is a real הלכה.
halacha. Real הלכה halacha is you go by the current size. That
seems to be a pretty good proof. So the גמרא says אמר
רבא Amar Raba so רבא Raba says you know what you're right.
Nobody can debate that you have to look at the current size
even those that say you go by the way it originally was.
Let's take a look. כל היכא דמעיקרא הוי ביה Kol heicha de-mei-ikara
havei beih if it originally had the right שיעור shiur which is
like this case of the meat of an old
animal והשתא לית ביה ve-hashta leit beih and now it doesn't have
the right שיעור לית ביה. leit beih. Everybody would have to admit
who cares what it used to be? Right now if I touch
this meat and the meat wasn't the right size who do I
care what it used to be in the past? It now is
not big enough to cause טומאה. tumah. So you know what you're
right. Even those that are of the camp that say you go
from what it used to be they would not say
that to an extreme. They would say that if right now it's
the wrong size then it doesn't have the power to do what
it is supposed to do. Okay so now let's look at the
reverse case. וכל היכא דמעיקרא לא הוי ביה והשתא הוי ביה Ve-kol
heicha de-mei-ikara lo havei beih ve-hashta havei beih if originally it didn't
have the right size and now it has the right size so
there you could be saying that maybe
biblically you go by its state now. He says no, that is
מדרבנן. mi-derabbanan. That also everybody would agree is only rabbinic. Why? Because
he's saying think about it if originally this thing wasn't the right
size it never had טומאה tumah to begin with. Okay now you
don't have to say it had טומאה tumah but it didn't have
the ability to communicate the טומאה tumah which every time we do
say anyway if it's less than כביצה ke-betzah but his point is
that if it didn't start with that status it's not going to
magically get that status later on. This works, I understand but this
is רבא's Raba claim. רבא Raba is actually trying to minimize the
debate because look let's use common sense. If right now it is
not big enough how could you say it is a problem right
now? Even if it is big enough right now if it didn't
start that way then also how can it be a problem right
now? How does it magically out of thin air get a new
status? Not magically. I understand that it is a more reasonable position
to say you always go by right now. I understand but רבא
Raba is trying to minimize this debate and רבא Raba is saying
that everybody would agree that what you really need is it has
to start that way so it starts with the status and it
stays that way so it retains the status. I saw very lovely
but they're obviously debating and the משנה's obviously saying that sometimes if
it changed a change happened. So here's where רבא's Raba going to
say change could all change could matter. כי פליגי Ki pligi the
beginning of נ"ד עמוד ב' nun-dalet amud bet
where they argue דהוה ביה כשיעור de-hava beih keshiur it started with
the right size וצמק ve-tzamak and it shriveled וחזר וטיפח ve-chazar ve-tipeach
and then it re-expanded like it shriveled because it was left out
of the sun then maybe some water moisture got back into it
and it re-expanded back to its old size. So it started with
the right size it ends the right size now it's possible to
say that it has its status. So question is having shrunk in
the middle will that be enough to lose the status permanently? Okay.
מר סבר one holds יש דיחוי באיסורא. yesh dichei be-issura. You normally
talk about דיחוי dichei by a קרבן korban if there was a
state where it couldn't be used as a קרבן korban it gets
pushed away. That's where the idea to disqualify for something good as
it were to be used for a קרבן. korban. But here we're
saying maybe it's a general idea about statuses. If it was the
status didn't apply for a particular period it shrunk and was too
short then that status can no longer apply to this object. יש
דיחוי באיסורא. Yesh dichei be-issura. So there was a time in the
middle where it was not the right size that means it stopped
having the status of טומאה tumah it can't get that status back.
Do we say that? ומר סבר אין דיחוי באיסורא U-mar savar ein
dichei be-issura or there is no pushing off. It started the right
size it ended the right size I don't care about what happened
in the middle it now has that status. So according to רבא
Raba and my point is is correctly a little bit annoyed says
there actually was something compelling about the position which is I don't
care about what it was originally I care about what it is
right now and right now the size whatever. רבא Raba is trying
to minimize it and רבא Raba certainly says it would not be
logical for anybody to say you go by now that if it's
not the right size now that somehow it has power because of
what it used to be. That's certainly not but in general he
tries to minimize and says everybody says you need to start with
the right size you need to end with the right size. The
only question is when it changes in the middle maybe is that
going to make a difference or not. Okay.
So now the גמרא says leave it to have it naturally or
do man-made?
It's a good question we'll see in a minute about not necessarily
about natural versus man-made but at least about what happens if the
change happened because of an outside ingredient. So let's take a look.
So right similar right. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
ומי איכא למאן דאמר דאית דיחוי? U-mi ika le-man de-amar de-it dichei?
Is there anybody that says there is דיחוי dichei that when it
loses its status it's not getting it back? והתנן Ve-hatnan we taught
in a משנה כביצה אוכלין שהניחה בחמה. Ke-betzah ochlin she-hinichah be-chamah. So
you have an egg's worth of food, food can also only Actual
versus man-made at least about what happens if the change happened because
of an outside ingredient, so let's take a look. Start right סימן,
Siman, right? So let's take a look at the גמרא. ומי איכא
למאן דאמר דיש דחוי אצל איסורין, Umi ika leman deamar deyesh dikhui
etzel issurin, is there anybody that says there is דחוי, dikhui, that
when it loses its status it's not gaining it back? But we
learned in a משנה: כביצה אוכלין שהניחה בחמה. Kebeitzah ochlin shehinicha bachamah.
So you have an egg's worth of food. Food can also only
become טמא tamei or transfer טומאה. tumah. There's a whole פרשה parsha
about becoming
טמא tamei בתורת be-torat whatever, only can transfer טומאה tumah if it's
the size of an egg. You have an egg's worth of food,
you left it out in the sun.
What?
Can we say כזית kezayit mean man-made?
Well, but this is טומאת אוכלין, tumat ochlin, it's whether it's the
source of טומאה tumah or a receiver of טומאה. tumah. Here we're
talking about as a receiver of טומאה tumah where it's more about
a כביצה. kebeitzah. Okay, anyway, שהניחה בחמה, shehinicha bachamah, you left it
out in the sun, ונתמעטו, venitmaatu, and they shriveled and it's not
a כביצה kebeitzah anymore.
וכן כזית מן המת, Vechen kezayit min hamet, כזית, kezayit, now here's
the thing, when it's a source of טומאה, tumah, not something like
food which receives טומאה, tumah, then the amount is a כזית, kezayit,
an olive's worth. So an olive's worth of a dead
corpse, כזית מן הנבלה, kezayit min haneveilah, a dead
animal, כעדשה מן השרץ, ka'adashah min hasheretz, by certain bug, not bugs
whatever, certain rodents, it goes by the size of a lentil
bean, וכזית פיגול וכזית נותר וכזית חלב, vekezayit pigul vekezayit notar vekezayit
chelev, a כזית kezayit of פיגול, pigul, נותר, notar, or חלב, chelev,
which are forbidden foods but also rabbinically communicate טומאה. tumah. In those
cases, טהורין, tehorin, if they shriveled, they're now טהור. tahor. Okay, that's
clearly the point that it now has to be the right size.
ואין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול ונותר וחלב, Ve-ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul
venotar vechelev, and if you ate them, you would not transgress the
prohibition of eating these forbidden foods. Now,
הניחם בגשמים ותפחו, henicham begeshamim vetaphachu, let's say now you left it
out in the rain and now they re-expanded because they absorbed the
moisture. What's their status? טמאין, tme'in, they become טמא tamei again.
וחייבין עליהם משום פיגול ונותר וטמא, Vechayavin aleihem mishum pigul venotar vetamei,
and you are חייב chayav if you eat them. And this is
quite fascinating because here we are like we are acknowledging that we
know the reason they expanded was not some inner process that occurred
that made them sort of, you know, it could have, right? Could
be that things are like releasing gases and things are expanding naturally,
but we understand that it's through the insertion of outside water and
we're still saying that since it started the right size and then
it lost water and now it's gone back to the right size,
we consider it to be the original thing and a כזית kezayit
and therefore creates טומאה tumah and you're חייב chayav if you eat
it. So you see, you ignore the middle state and you're חייב.
chayav. תיובתא למאן דאמר יש דחוי באיסורין תיובתא, Tiyuvta leman deamar yesh
dikhui be-issurin tiyuvta,
this is a complete contradiction, here is exactly the case we're describing,
and we see that you go by the size that it is
right now even if there was a state where it was not.
And again, it is quite fascinating because here we know that it's
actually getting external liquid. Now, it is replacing the liquid it lost,
but we do know it's getting it from the outside. Raises also
interesting questions about the halachic status about reconstituted fruits, right? There was
a תשובה tshuvah that somebody once wrote to, I think it's the
ציץ אליעזר, Tzitz Eliezer, a שאלה, sheila, which is: can I make
קידוש Kiddush on reconstituted grape juice? Is it considered significant enough to
still make קידוש Kiddush on? And his תשובה tshuvah starts by saying,
"Before you ask me if you can make קידוש Kiddush on it,
you should ask me if you can say בורא פרי הגפן Borei
Peri Hagafen on it." So, you know, what is the halachic status
of something that you extract the liquid from and then put other
liquid back in and make it like it was, like grape juice
from concentrate? What? Yeah, grape juice from concentrate, right. Anyway, so that
is actually essentially what we're asking here and here, at least the
ברייתא Braitah is saying that when it comes to טומאה tumah and
forbidden foods whatever, it actually does get back that original status. So
again, what we are saying is that we are sort of minimizing
the debate. It certainly needs the size now. רבא Rava is saying
not only does it need the size now, it needed to have
started with the right size. The only issue is if it shrunk
in the middle and here we're saying that that is inconsequential even
if then the way it re-expanded was through outside liquid. So we
will pick up with this tomorrow.